Guide to the David Anderson Photographs from "On Wall Street" 1980-2002 PR 414
New-York Historical Society
David Anderson photographs from "On Wall Street"
1980-2002
New-York Historical Society
Anderson, David, 1943-
PR 414
5.5 Linear feet in 3 flat boxes.
78 gelatin silver prints by David Anderson of skyscrapers and building details in the Financial District that appeared in his book "On Wall Street: Architectural Photographs of Lower Manhattan, 1980-2000" (2012).
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers by appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of David Anderson, 2019 (accession no. PPAC-2019-049).
Arrangement
The photographs (all signed, some matted) are segregated by size in three flat boxes: 11 x 14-inch prints in Box 1, and 16 x 20-inch prints in Boxes 2-3.
Biographical note
David V. Anderson was born in Lincoln, Nebraska in 1943. He began his photographic career at the New York Daily News in 1961 as a copy boy with the encouragement of Alfred Eisenstaedt at Life Magazine. From 1969 to 1983 he was a cinematographer based in New York City who specialized in commercials and documentaries. He also photographed two independent films directed by artist Nancy Graves, including "Isy Boukir," which was acquired for the collection of films at the Museum of Modern Art. Since 1983 he has worked as an architectural photographer. He is the author of "On Wall Street: Architectural Photographs of Lower Manhattan, 1980-2000," published by George F. Thompson Publishing. His web site is davidvanderson.com.
His photographs are in the collections of: Amon Carter Museum of American Art, Brooklyn Museum, Canadian Centre for Architecture, Library of Congress, Fralin Museum at the University of Virginia, Museum of the City of New York, New York Public Library, Sheldon Museum of Art at the University of Nebraska, and the Loeb Art Center at Vassar College.
[This biography was supplied by the photographer.]
Related Materials
David Anderson included with his gift of these photographs a copy of the book in which they were published: On Wall Street: Architectural Photographs of Lower Manhattan, 1980-2000 (Staunton, Virginia: George F. Thompson, 2012). Request it through its catalog record.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains 78 gelatin silver prints of images taken by David Anderson that appear in his book "On Wall Street: Architectural Photographs of Lower Manhattan, 1980-2000" (Staunton, Virginia: George F. Thompson, 2012). Specific addresses and buildings include:
Beaver Street, No. 65
Broad Street, Nos. 67 and 90
Broadway, Nos. 1, 25, 26, 100, 111, 195, and 346
Exchange Place, No. 20
Liberty Street, No. 55
Maiden Lane, No. 90
Nassau Street, No. 99
Old Slip, No. 48
Park Row, No. 15
Pine Street, Nos. 56 and 70
South William Street, No. 9
State Street, No. 7
Vesey Street, No. 20
Wall Street, Nos. 1, 16, 23, 35, 40, 48, 52, 55, and 74
West Street, No. 140
Chamber of Commerce
City Hall
Federal Hall National Memorial
Federal Reserve Bank
Municipal Building
New York Stock Exchange
St. Paul's Chapel
Trinity Church
Tweed Courthouse
U.S. Courthouse
U.S. Customs House
Woolworth Building
World Trade Center
The collection includes a DVD recording of a book talk Anderson gave at the Skyscraper Museum on June 26, 2013, which is viewable online at this link.
Architectural photography -- New York (State) -- New York.; Skyscrapers -- New York (State) -- New York -- Photographs.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs.; Wall Street (New York, N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Photographs.; Gelatin silver prints.; Alexander Hamilton United States Custom House (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.; Woolworth Building (New York, N.Y.) -- Photographs.
- "On Wall Street": 11 x 14-inch prints (44)
  Arrangement
  Numbers preceding each title were supplied by the photographer; the processing archivist has copied these in pencil to the back of each photograph's mount. Page numbers following each title indicate that photograph's position in the book "On Wall Street: Architectural Photographs of Lower Manhattan, 1980-2000" (Staunton, Virginia: George F. Thompson, 2012).
  - 01) Aerial view of Wall Street area (page 2), 2000 (Box 1)
  - 02) View from 25 Broadway (page 24), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 03) 1 and 16 Wall Street (page 27), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 04) Pyramid, 16 Wall Street (page 29), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 05) 26th Floor, 16 Wall Street (page 31), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 06) Side door, 1 Wall Street (page 33), 1980 (Box 1)
  - 07) Rooftop, 40 Wall Street (page 39), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 08) 48 and 52 Wall Street (page 40), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 09) Eagle, 48 Wall Street (page 41), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 10) Rear Gate, U.S. Customs House (page 68), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 11) First Class Door, 1 Broadway (page 51), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 12) 25 Broadway, Three Faces (page 50), 1983 (Box 1)
  - 13) 26 Broadway (page 56), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 14) 26 Broadway, South Side (page 57), 1998 (Box 1)
  - 15) Tower, 26 Broadway (page 55), 1996 (Box 1)
  - 16) Detail, 100 Broadway (page 87), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 17) 111 Broadway (page 58), 1983 (Box 1)
  - 18) Cupola, 111 Broadway (page 59), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 19) Detail, 43rd Floor, Woolworth Building (page 64), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 20) Side View, Gable, Woolworth Building (page 65), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 21) South Gable, Woolworth Building (page 63), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 22) Cooper [copper?], Woolworth Building (page 66), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 23) St. Paul's Chapel (page 76), 1980 (Box 1)
  - 24) 20 Vesey Street (page 79), 1999 (Box 1)
  - 25) Detail, 140 West Street (page 93), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 26) 99 Nassau Street (page 90), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 27) U.S. Courthouse and Municipal Building (page 80), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 28) Municipal Building (page 81), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 29) Steps, City Hall (page 83), 1980 (Box 1)
  - 30) Tweed Courthouse, Northwest Façade (page 118), 2002 (Box 1)
  - 31) 346 Broadway (page 77), 1999 (Box 1)
  - 32) 67 Broad Street (page 90), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 33) 90 Broad Street (page 85), 1996 (Box 1)
  - 34) 7 State Street (page 47), 2000 (Box 1)
  - 35) 9 South William Street (page 49), 1980 (Box 1)
  - 36) 70 Pine Street (page 95), 1989 (Box 1)
  - 37) Detail, South Side, 70 Pine Street (page 96), 1987 (Box 1)
  - 38) Detail, 48 Old Slip (page 99), 1980 (Box 1)
  - 39) Federal Reserve Bank (page 98), 1981 (Box 1)
  - 40) Detail, 90 Maiden Lane (page 97), 1982 (Box 1)
  - 41) Alligator, 55 Liberty Street (page 100), 1983 (Box 1)
  - 42) Chamber of Commerce (page 91), 2000 (Box 1)
  - 43) Ram's Head, 65 Beaver Street (page 104), 1991 (Box 1)
  - 44) World Trade Center (page 109), 1987 (Box 1)
- "On Wall Street": 16 x 20-inch prints (34)
  - 01) Door, 35 Wall Street (page 10), 1980 (Box 2)
  - 02) Wall Street Looking West (page 23), 1987 (Box 2)
  - 03) View From 67 Wall Street (page 26), 1987 (Box 2)
  - 04) Broad Street Looking North (page 25), 1996 (Box 2)
  - 05) 16 Wall Street (page 28), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 06) Trinity Church and 1 Wall Street (page 32), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 07) New York Stock Exchange (page 34), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 08) New York Stock Exchange from Federal Hall (page 35), 1985 (Box 2)
  - 09) Steps, 23 Wall Street (page 37), 1980 (Box 2)
  - 10) Federal Hall National Memorial (page 36), 2000 (Box 2)
  - 11) Columns, 55 Wall Street (page 45), 1987 (Box 2)
  - 12) Detail, 74 Wall Street (page 69), 1999 (Box 2)
  - 13) U.S. Customs House (page 44), 1983 (Box 2)
  - 14) Steps, U.S. Customs House (page 42), 1983 (Box 2)
  - 15) West Wall, U.S. Customs House (page 43), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 16) 19th Floor, 25 Broadway (page 52), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 17) Sea Nymph, 19th Floor, 25 Broadway (page 53), 1981 (Box 2)
  - 18) Detail, Roof, 195 Broadway (page 60), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 19) Door, 195 Broadway (page 61), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 20) Roof, 195 Broadway (page 71), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 21) View from Park Place (page 72), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 22) Woolworth Building (page 73), 1982 (Box 3)
  - 23) Indian and Snake, Woolworth Building (page 67), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 24) 15 Park Row (page 74), 1980 (Box 3)
  - 25) North Tower, 15 Park Row (page 75), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 26) Arcade, Municipal Building (82), 1984 (Box 3)
  - 27) Detail, 15 William Street (page 88), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 28) 56 Pine Street (page 89), 1987 (Box 3)
  - 29) View from Hanover Street (page 101), 1991 (Box 3)
  - 30) Windows, 22 William Street (page 92), 1991 (Box 3)
  - 31) Exchange Place from Pearl Street (page 103), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 32) Door, 22 William Street (page 105), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 33) Roof, 20 Exchange Place (page 106), 1981 (Box 3)
  - 34) Head, 20 Exchange Place (page 107), 1981 (Box 3)